hello everybody my name is Grand mell
with the political vigilante I'm
obviously not in my studio I'm in an
illustrious hotel room on the road Ron
Falcone and I are doing our progressive
comedy tour and I have very special
guests here former CIA whistleblower
John Kerry aku and John thank you so
much for taking time today my pleasure
first let's give people just some
context to know who you are tell us your
history with the CIA and what happened
when you did the whistleblowing and when
and what brought all that and what was
the kind of fallout from that sure my
name is John Kiriakou I spent 15 years
with the CIA the first half in analysis
the second half in counterterrorism
operations after 9/11 I was the chief of
CIA counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan and in that capacity I led a
series of raids that resulted in the
capture of a guy named Abu Zubaydah who
we believed at the time was the number
three al Qaeda it turned out he was not
the number three okay although he was a
bad man
we captured him and he was sent to a
secret prison where several months later
he was tortured he was the first person
to undergo waterboarding and a wide
variety of other torture techniques
I left the CIA in 2004 and in 2007 after
having waited three half years for
somebody to come out and say something
about the torture program I decided to
just do it myself and so I agreed to
give an interview to ABC News in
December of 2007 in which I said three
things I said that the CIA was torturing
his prisoners I said that torture was
official US government policy not the
result of a rogue as President Bush had
said and I said that the torture program
had been personally approved by the
President as you can imagine the FBI
began investigating me the very next day
they investigated me for a year from
December of oh seven until December of
Oh
I had not committed a crime and so they
closed the case three
weeks later Barack Obama becomes
president and appoints an old nemesis of
mine John Brennan as the deputy national
security advisor I did not know that
John Brennan then secretly asked the
Justice Department to reopen the case
against me and so for the next three
years I had no idea that I was under
24-hour surveillance that my emails were
being intercepted that my phone calls
were being monitored and in January of
2012 I was arrested and charged with
five felonies including three counts of
espionage coming out of that ABC News
interview espionage is one of the
greatest crimes with which an American
can be charged and it sometimes carries
with it the death penalty I was looking
at 45 years in prison I fought it up
until the bitter end I hadn't committed
espionage until eventually the
government as as onerous as it was for
me they had to find the admit that I
hadn't committed they dropped those
three charges but I typically to a
lesser count just to make the thing go
away I did 23 months in a federal prison
got out in 2015 and I've been working on
things like prison reform sentencing
reform human rights civil rights civil
liberties ever since Wow
yeah they can't charge you for espionage
because you have to work with a like an
enemy of country right like a foreign
country that's a well yeah I mean that's
that's what in the past there was a
dangerous precedent okay so my judge
said that she would not respect that
precedent for a foreign country she said
that she was going to she was going to
define espionage as providing National
Defense information to any person not
entitled to receive it and my lawyer
said your honor Reese thing that a
person can accidentally commit espionage
or that a journalist in commit espionage
and she said that's exactly what I'm
saying
and so we kind of knew we were doomed
from the beginning there was no getting
out of it you know I I'm gonna I'm gonna
cut to the chase early on in this talk
my lawyers told me that was a bitter
pill to swallow we first said it but it
turned out to be so wise and so correct
I decided to turn down the government's
author of 23 months in prison and to go
to trial because I believed that once I
could get in front of a jury they would
see how ridiculous this was I am a
patriot I'm not a criminal and I
certainly didn't commit espionage and he
stopped me and he said you know what
your problem is your problem is that you
think this is about justice and it's not
about justice
it's about mitigating damage take the
deal and I took the deal Wow
yeah well that's that's fascinating to
me on so many levels I want to ask you
later a little bit what your opinion of
Gina Haspel is but who didn't she not
create the enhanced interrogation
program or indeed she did you know when
Gina was I worked for Gina she was my
boss in the CIA's Counterterrorism
Center we called her bloody Gina bloody
Gina hassle and it was because she went
out to the secret site just to sit and
watch a torture session just for the
hell of it just because she wanted to
she later became the chief of the zebra
sight and she was later after that the
chief of Guantanamo base but yeah Jeter
was one of the godmothers of the of the
torture program she was in up to her
neck when she was named CIA director
Washington Post called me and they asked
me to write an op-ed they told me they
gave me 1,200 words which is unheard of
and so I did I wrote it I said look you
know I think it's wonderful that the
president wants to name a woman as the
CIA director the CIA's been run by by
white men for the past 70 years just not
this woman there are a dozen two dozen
other women out there who do terrific
CIA directors but naming Gina Haskell
sends a message to the work force and
the message is that you can commit war
crimes you can commit crimes against
humanity you can carry out a torture
program or open up a series of secret
prisons
launched an international kidnapping
operation called rendition and not only
are you not going to be prosecuted you
can be promoted all the way to director
that's exactly the message that we
should not be sending either to the
workforce or to our friends and allies
yeah because I mean I told I had read
not only did she go to these black sites
to watch the torture she like enjoyed it
like she enjoyed it
yes that's correct you know what kind of
psychopath was sitting on a torture
session just for the heck of it if you
fly halfway around the world to watch a
man be tortured and humiliated just to
say that you did one people don't do
things like that yeah that's that's
that's alarming but also in some ways
not surprising that that's who the CIA
would want to in charge of them of their
organization as someone that's basically
a sociopath and you know one of the
things that was that was a shock to me
was in her her confirmation hearing
before the Senate Select Committee on
Intelligence
she was pressed by Senator Ron Wyden the
Democrat of Oregon and she finally
finally admitted that the program was a
mistake that it shouldn't have been done
and it didn't result in a collection of
any actionable intelligence and that was
funny to me and Shawn King because she
was one of those counselors who had been
trying to perpetuate this lie from 2002
onward that the torture program did
result in the collection of actionable
intelligence
it just didn't that was a lie and they
kept repeating the line hoping that it
was stick right because as we know I
mean I think even John McCain said this
I mean you can torture I mean you could
get me to say anything you know you can
get anyone to say anything if you
torture them enough right especially if
they're sleep rived or whatever they
just want it to end and even if that or
even as a victim the torture victim
tells you what you want to hear even if
he tells you the truth he's going to
tell you so much that you have to turn
all that
/ - a team of analysts and it's going to
take them six months to figure out what
was true and what was nonsense and what
was just made up and what was partly
true and partly not true
or speculation or whatever and by then
the bomb you were trying to defuse has
already gone off and killed 200 people
Wow Wow
so what yeah this is hold ticking time
bomb scenario this comes right out of
Hollywood there is no such thing as a
ticking time bomb scenario you can't
torture someone and say you know give me
the code to shut the bomb off and then
he gives you the code really doesn't
work like that let me be really specific
here - the actionable intelligence that
that Gina Haskell and Jose Rodriguez and
other pro torturers CIA officers clean -
extracted from Abu Zubaydah thanks to
these torture techniques was actually
information that was gathered by an FBI
agent and at least some fun now I'm me
some fun was I work about me in Pakistan
and believe me it's like a kid a gut to
have to complement the FBI but they're
really really good right so they know
what they're doing
so what Ali did is once Abu Zubaydah was
healthy enough to be interviewed
he sat across the table from him he
offered him a cigarette and a cup of tea
and some dates and he engaged him in
conversation and it took weeks before I
was a day to finally opened his mouth
and started talking but once he started
talking he gave all the information that
was new to us on the structure of
al-qaeda on the location of al-qaeda
cells in Europe on the name moved on who
it turned out was Khalid Sheikh Mohammed
the mastermind of the 9/11 attacks but
CIA was frustrated because I he was
taking a long time and so George Tenet
the CIA director asked President Bush to
expel all the FBI agents from the
country the secret site he did that and
so to contract psychiatrists Mitchell
and Jessen took over and immediately
within two hours began to torture I was
a beta well they started with the
techniques they started with
waterboarding when we stay we're
supposed to actually finish with not
start with he convulsed he went into
seizures his heart stopped beating he
had to be revived well they couldn't say
that to headquarters so they wrote to
headquarters we did the techniques he
cracked he told us everything and what
they did is they just repeated at least
some funds information because they knew
that the FBI computer system and the CIA
computer system were not compatible and
so they were not sharing information so
the FBI was thinking boy obvious if I'm
did a really great job and at the CIA
they're thinking wow this torture
program really works it was all a lie
that's that's amazing that's amazing to
me haha I mean how do you look at like
today's CIA and what's happening and
where in what war and eight or nine
countries yeah are they effective at all
are they just causing more problems
they're not effective at all
and I say that you know with like a pain
in my heart because I devoted the better
part of my adult life to the CIA I like
I say I was a patriot I wanted to serve
my country I wanted to do the right
thing and keep Americans safe and it'll
turn out to be [__] you know doesn't
need to be easy anymore
they miss they have missed all of the
major global political events of the
last century from you know the Berlin
Wall to the Iranian Revolution to the
collapse of communism you name it
they've got it wrong time and time again
you got it wrong and so it's time to do
something different what would you
suggest that be well John Kennedy
famously said that he wanted to break
the CIA to a thousand pieces and
scattered to the winds that was repeated
in 1976 in a book by daniel patrick
moynihan
a senator from new york one hand was
mocked when that book came out in 1976
but he was onto something you have the
best analysis and the intelligence
community does not come from the CIA
comes from the State Department's Bureau
and research well there's also a human
collection outfit at the Pentagon called
DHS not the Department of Homeland
Security but defense human services
defense human intelligence services they
recruit spies to steal secrets just as
well as the CIA does and in terms of of
tech issues and interception I mean
that's what that's all gonna say does so
why you have this redundant organization
Langley that is actually sort of in
charge the fact that we charge of the
intelligence community when they're the
ones getting it wrong all the time
wow that's an excellent that is an
excellent point so
you